<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>Schartz&#039;s</title>
    <link href="" />
    <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="/blog/feed.atom" />
    <updated>2019-06-02T15:16:16+05:30</updated>
    <id>/blog/feed.atom</id>
    <author>
        <name>Schartz Rehan</name>
    </author>
                <entry>
    <id>/blog/06-02-2019-install-tfgpu131-on-ubuntu</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="/blog/06-02-2019-install-tfgpu131-on-ubuntu" />
    <title>Install Tensorflow GPU 1.13 on Elementary OS Juno (Ubuntu 18.04)</title>
    <published>2019-06-02T05:30:00+05:30</published>
    <updated>2019-06-02T05:30:00+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Schartz Rehan</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">Setting up Tensorflow with GPU support gave me good deal of pain. Internet is full of tutorials
with older releases of Tensorflow. Some of them use an approach of installing CUDA toolkit via apt.
This approach is not appropriate because of a number of......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p>Setting up Tensorflow with GPU support gave me good deal of pain. Internet is full of tutorials
with older releases of Tensorflow. Some of them use an approach of installing CUDA toolkit via apt.
This approach is not appropriate because of a number of reasons.<br />
Tensorflow 2.0 is in alpha stage now.
It has a planned stable release in second quarter of 2019. Soon enough I'll be upgrading to latest stable.<br />
Nvidia drivers have a penchant for being compatible with specific versions of CUDA toolkit, to make matters
a bit more complicated Tensorflow requires a specific version of Nvidia drivers.  </p>
<p>Ubuntu graphics-driver ppa has latest Nvidia drivers <code>nvidia-driver-430</code> at the time of writing. However, requirements for
Tensorflow 13.1 are <code>nvidia-driver-410</code> and <code>cuda-toolkit-10.0</code>. cuDNN 7.5.0 is also required for Tensorflow.  </p>
<p>Let's begin with a clean install.</p>
<h2>Step1: Install Nvidia drivers</h2>
<p>If you have <code>nvidia-driver-410</code> meta package installed, you can skip this step.</p>
<p>Start by adding Ubuntu Graphics Driver PPA if not already added. </p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">sudo add-apt-repository ppa:graphics-drivers/ppa    
sudo apt-get update</code></pre>
<p>Remove any nvidia drivers. We are doing a clean install</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">sudo apt-get purge nvidia* 
sudo apt-get autoremove 
sudo apt-get autoclean 
sudo rm -rf /usr/local/cuda*</code></pre>
<p>If you have a Secure Boot UEFI enabled system it will ask you to set a password which
you'll need to enter at the time of reboot. This is a one time only process.
Now reboot your system.  </p>
<p>Check if install was successful by running following</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">nvidia-smi</code></pre>
<p>It should print something similar to following.  </p>
<p><img src="/assets/img/posts/nvidiasmi.png" alt="Blog starter template screenshot" />  </p>
<p>Notice the version of CUDA toolkit stated by the driver.
Version 410 of nvidia driver for Linux is only compatible with CUDA toolkit version 10.<br />
If your screen resolution is messed up after driver install, fix it with following.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">sudo nvidia-xconfig</code></pre>
<h2>Step2: Install CUDA toolkit 10.0</h2>
<p>Install the dependencies</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">sudo apt-get install g++ freeglut3-dev build-essential libx11-dev libxmu-dev libxi-dev libglu1-mesa libglu1-mesa-dev</code></pre>
<p>Head over to <a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/cuda-10.0-download-archive">https://developer.nvidia.com/cuda-10.0-download-archive</a>
and download the CUDA archive.  Make sure to download runfile.  </p>
<p><img src="/assets/img/posts/cudatoolkit.png" alt="Blog starter template screenshot" />  </p>
<p>Install it.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">sudo sh cuda_10.0.130_410.48_linux.run</code></pre>
<p>In the installation process installer will complain that you are about to install an unsupported configuration.
Answer <code>yes</code> to that. Installer complains about 'unsupported configuration', because it's not the latest version of CUDA toolkit.
However, latest stable version of Tensorflow (1.13 at the time of writing) requires CUDA 10.0 specifically.<br />
Installer will also ask to add a symlink. Answer <code>yes</code> to that as well.<br />
Finally add following to your <code>~/.bashrc</code> and/or <code>~/.zshrc</code> in accordance with whichever shell you use.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">export PATH=/usr/local/cuda-10.0/bin${PATH:+:${PATH}}
export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=/usr/local/cuda-10.0/lib64${LD_LIBRARY_PATH:+:${LD_LIBRARY_PATH}}</code></pre>
<p>Afterwards load these PATH additions in your current shell session as well as run <code>ldconfig</code>
Run <code>source ~/.zshrc</code> if you are in Z shell.</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">source ~/.bashrc
sudo ldconfig</code></pre>
<h2>Step3: Install cuDNN 7.5.0</h2>
<p>Go to <a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/rdp/cudnn-archive">https://developer.nvidia.com/rdp/cudnn-archive</a> and click download cuDNN button.
Nvidia will require you to create an account (if you don't already have one). After logging into your Nvidia Developer Account accept the agreement
Click on cuDNN archive which says <code>Download cuDNN v7.5.0 (Feb 21, 2019), for CUDA 10.0</code> and download <code>cuDNN Library for Linux</code>
<a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/compute/machine-learning/cudnn/secure/v7.5.0.56/prod/10.0_20190219/cudnn-10.0-linux-x64-v7.5.0.56.tgz">Here is the direct download link to the same.</a><br />
But there is no guarantee that it will work all the time. If the direct doesn't work, follow above steps.<br />
Once you have downloaded the cuDNN archive put it at correct place by running:</p>
<pre><code class="language-blade">tar -xf cudnn-10.0-linux-x64-v7.5.0.56.tgz
sudo cp -R cuda/include/* /usr/local/cuda-10.0/include
sudo cp -R cuda/lib64/* /usr/local/cuda-10.0/lib64</code></pre>
<p>Also install a small dependency </p>
<pre><code class="language-blade">sudo apt-get install libcupti-dev</code></pre>
<p>Add following to your <code>~/.bashrc</code> or <code>~/.zshrc</code></p>
<pre><code class="language-blade">export LD_LIBRARY_PATH=/usr/local/cuda/extras/CUPTI/lib64:$LD_LIBRARY_PATH</code></pre>
<p>And finally</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">source ~/.bashrc
sudo ldconfig</code></pre>
<h2>Step4: Test it</h2>
<p>It's recommended that you have a virtual environment for this.
I prefer <code>virtualenvwrapper</code>.
You can use any tool to create virtual env.</p>
<pre><code class="language-blade">mkvirtualenv tfgpu
workon tfgpu
pip install tensorflow-gpu==1.13.1
pip show tensorflow-gpu</code></pre>
<p>It should show something like this </p>
<p><img src="/assets/img/posts/tf.png" alt="Blog starter template screenshot" /></p>
<p>Now go build some <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_intelligence">AI</a> </p>    ]]></content>
</entry>
            <entry>
    <id>/blog/my-first-blog-post</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="/blog/my-first-blog-post" />
    <title>Hello Blogging</title>
    <published>2019-05-29T05:30:00+05:30</published>
    <updated>2019-05-29T05:30:00+05:30</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Schartz Rehan</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;code&gt;This is the start of your first blog post.&lt;/code&gt;  
This is what JigSaw told me as I booted things up for my first (serious-ish) blogging attempt.
I have been thinking about creating a blog for quite sometime. And finally my procrastination was......</summary>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
        <p><code>This is the start of your first blog post.</code>  </p>
<p>This is what JigSaw told me as I booted things up for my first (serious-ish) blogging attempt.
I have been thinking about creating a blog for quite sometime. And finally my procrastination was beaten, this blog is here.  </p>
<p>I am not very sure about the direction for this blog. I'll be mostly documenting about the things I've been doing and an occasional <code>thought_dump()</code> will be present.  </p>
<p>The idea of running an entire blog from a Git repository seems interesting and a bit bewitching.  </p>
<p>I have interest in a lot of things. Consequently, there will be writings about a lot of things. And there will be a bunch of Computer Science, Programming and Mathematics.<br />
You have been warned.</p>    ]]></content>
</entry>
    </feed>
